<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-01T16:23:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">de Duve PhD students’ Society</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>de Duve PhD Students' Society</name></author><entry><title type="html">How to pitch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/02/22/how_to_pitch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to pitch" /><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/02/22/how_to_pitch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/02/22/how_to_pitch.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a brief summary of the workshop held during the virtual 
FORUM PRO 2021. The workshop was given by Camille Wuidar (UpSkill) and
Guillaume Thieffry (UCLouvain). There are three main pillars that 
allow for an efficient pitch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The personal presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An efficient speech should not last longer than 2 minutes, that’s the
absolute maximum! Also, keep in mind that at most 30 % of your speech
will be effectively received by your audience so avoid too many details
and go to the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;form&quot;&gt;Form&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of your speech is very importante. You can focus your
audience’ attention on at most 3 topics and those topics should have 
clear links and should lead to an emotional response. There are 3
major framework that can help you link your different topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;timeline&lt;/strong&gt;: make use of temporal structure in your speach, like
past, present and future. But watch out to not fall into a boring 
chronological enumeration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thematic&lt;/strong&gt; structure: focus on 3 themes that you’ll list in your 
intro. For instance, you could focus on three different roles you 
played in your previous job or study track.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan of action&lt;/strong&gt;: speak as if your were developing a new project
and point out 3 issues that you could contribute to solve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you could mix those different frameworks. The key point is 
that your rely on three pillars that should be easy to remember!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content of pitch is divided in 4 points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;catch&lt;/strong&gt;: the first step is to grasp the attention of your 
target and put him in the context of your speach. For instance, 
could approach someone with an anecdote or an interesting scientific
fact, or an intriguing question.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;presentatio&lt;/strong&gt;: briefly describe yourself in 2-3 sentence, that’s
very short so make sure to include only relevant information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make use of the &lt;strong&gt;3-topic framework&lt;/strong&gt;. You should be practical and
include for instance some examples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;: tell what is your objective and how it can 
profit to your audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having first impression is inevitable, so make sure your audience has 
a good first impression of you. This impression is already settles 
during the 4 x 20 rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20 first words. Words represent 10% of the impact of your pitch.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20 first gestures (35% of the total impact).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20 cm of the visage. Pay attention to your gaze, smile, facial 
expression, that’s 55% of the impact of your pitch.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20 first seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Vanderaa</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="training" /><summary type="html">This post is a brief summary of the workshop held during the virtual FORUM PRO 2021. The workshop was given by Camille Wuidar (UpSkill) and Guillaume Thieffry (UCLouvain). There are three main pillars that allow for an efficient pitch:</summary></entry></feed>