<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-31T12:56:33+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">de Duve PhD students’ Society</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>de Duve PhD Students' Society</name></author><entry><title type="html">How to pitch</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/05/04/how_to_pitch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to pitch" /><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/05/04/how_to_pitch</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/05/04/how_to_pitch.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a brief summary of the workshop held during the virtual 
FORUM PRO 2021. The workshop was given by Camille Wuidar (UpSkill) and
Guillaume Thieffry (UCLouvain). There are three main pillars that 
allow for an efficient pitch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The personal presentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An efficient speech should not last longer than 2 minutes, that’s the
absolute maximum! Also, keep in mind that at most 30 % of your speech
will be effectively received by your audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;form&quot;&gt;Form&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Vanderaa</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="training" /><summary type="html">This post is a brief summary of the workshop held during the virtual FORUM PRO 2021. The workshop was given by Camille Wuidar (UpSkill) and Guillaume Thieffry (UCLouvain). There are three main pillars that allow for an efficient pitch:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SMCS - Data visualisation and advanced tools in R</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/05/04/SMCS_data_vis_R.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SMCS - Data visualisation and advanced tools in R" /><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/05/04/SMCS_data_vis_R</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/05/04/SMCS_data_vis_R.html">&lt;p&gt;The R language is a computing environment and a very flexible and rich
progamming language used for statistical data analysis. It’s a free 
and open source software that is regularly enriched with new libraries
of functions provided by users. In particular, everyone can create a 
package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This training is offered by the &lt;strong&gt;SMCS&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objectives&quot;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this training, the participant will be familiar with
different data visualisation tools in R. He will also learn how to
efficiently reproduce the same analysis and how to include R outputs 
in a document (pdf, word…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic knowledge of R is required (cf. the first day of the training 
hereafter): &lt;em&gt;Introduction to data analysis with R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Efficient data visualisation : R base graphics and ggplot2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Efficient programmation : loops and functions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online through TEAMS&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Vanderaa</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="training" /><summary type="html">The R language is a computing environment and a very flexible and rich progamming language used for statistical data analysis. It’s a free and open source software that is regularly enriched with new libraries of functions provided by users. In particular, everyone can create a package.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">de Duve PhD day 2021</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/05/03/PhD_day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="de Duve PhD day 2021" /><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/05/03/PhD_day</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/05/03/PhD_day.html">&lt;p&gt;The PhD day of the de Duve Institute is an event created by the 
students for the students and more precisely by the de Duve students’ 
society. The concept is that during one day all the PhD students 
gather and have the opportunity to present their work to their peers 
through a poster or a presentation session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our objective is that the de Duve Institute becomes a united 
scientific community in the next years, and this starts with the PhD 
Day ! Even though the event will finally be online, we hope to provide
a nice environment for sharing research projects and connecting with 
other PhD students as well as to feed the scientific minds with 
various interesting scientific topics and stimulating discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The date to save in your calendar is the &lt;strong&gt;26th of May 2021&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poster-session&quot;&gt;Poster session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second year students have the responsibility to participate to the 
poster session! In brief, they are being asked to create a poster about 
their research project and to expose it during the morning session of 
this event. The PI, Post-Doc and other PhD students will have the
opportunity to take a look and ask questions or more details about the
project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the organization, we ask second year students to send us the 
abstract of their poster for the 15th of May (max 1 page) as well as 
the ppt of it for the 21st of May to Juliette Vanderroost 
(juliette.vanderroost@uclouvain.be). We also ask to send the ppt of 
the poster for the 21st of May, as well as a 2 min recording that
introduces the student and their research work and make other 
participants want to take a closer look at the poster. This super 
short introducing speech should not be a detailed explanation, but 
rather a trailer / teasing to try to get the audience’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;talk-sessions&quot;&gt;Talk sessions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TBA&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Vanderaa</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="event" /><summary type="html">The PhD day of the de Duve Institute is an event created by the students for the students and more precisely by the de Duve students’ society. The concept is that during one day all the PhD students gather and have the opportunity to present their work to their peers through a poster or a presentation session.</summary></entry></feed>